Guide to the Intercollegiate Socialist Society Records TAM.048
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Intercollegiate Socialist Society Records
1900-1921
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Intercollegiate Socialist Society (U.S.)
TAM.048
4.5 Linear Feet in 9 manuscript boxes.
The Intercollegiate Socialist Society (ISS), an on-campus student and faculty organization, was established in New York in 1905. The ISS established numerous study and reading groups, sponsored rallies and lecture engagements for prominent socialists, published book lists and pamphlets relating to a variety of socialist issues and held occasional national meetings and annual conventions. In 1921, the ISS changed its name to the League for Industrial Democracy so as to reflect its then older constituency and broader objectives. Harry W. Laidler was the organizing secretary of the ISS from 1910 to 1921 and the executive director of the League for Industrial Democracy from 1921 to 1956. The collection includes: correspondence, financial and membership records, executive committee minutes, organizing secretary reports, pamphlets, booklets, office materials, Bulletin of the Intercollegiate Socialist Society, 1908-1912, and newspaper clippings.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Possibly donated by Harry Laidler in 1970. The accession number associated with this collection is 1970.003.
Original correspondence, bulletins and pamphlets found in repository in May 2014 were added to this collection. The accession number associated with this material is 2014.089.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical Note
The Intercollegiate Socialist Society (ISS) was established by a prominent group of socialists in New York in 1905. Among the founding members of the ISS were James Graham Phelps Stokes, Charlotte Perkins Gilman, William English Walling, Thomas Wentworth Higginson, Leonard D. Abbott, Jack London, Upton Sinclair, B. O. Flowers, Clarence Darrow, and Oscar Lovell Triggs. The ISS was organized for the purpose of promoting the study and advocacy of socialism among college students and faculty members. During its most productive years, the ISS had active chapters on many campuses across the country, particularly in the eastern and Midwestern states. As a socialist educational organization, the ISS established numerous study and reading groups, sponsored rallies and lecture engagements for prominent socialists, published book lists and pamphlets relating to a variety of socialist issues, and held occasional national meetings and annual conventions. In 1921, the ISS changed its name to the League for Industrial Democracy so as to reflect its then older constituency and broader objectives.
Sources:
The Intercollegiate Socialist Society, 1905-1921: Origins of the Modern American Student Movement/ Max Horn. Boulder, Colo.: Westview Press, 1979. 259 p.
Scope and Contents
The Intercollegiate Socialist Society Records, 1900-1921, originate from the papers of Harry W. Laidler. (Laidler was the organizing secretary of the ISS from 1910 to 1921 and the executive director of the League for Industrial Democracy from 1921 to 1956.) The collection consists five series, divided into 29 subject files (some contain more than one folder of material), including correspondence; financial and membership records; Executive Committee minutes; Organizing Secretary reports; printed, mimeographed, and office materials; and newspaper clippings.
The contents of each subject file have been arranged chronologically, with all undated items placed at the end of the file. Each subject file has been assigned a frame number and has been cited in the complete reel list which follows this description of the arrangement of the collection. In the representative frame number, XII:1, the number "1" stands for the first subject file, while the roman numeral "XII" indicates that the ISS Records are the 12th of the 19 collections in the microfilm set Socialist Collections in the Tamiment Library, 1872-1956.
The second largest quantity of records in this collection is the correspondence (XII:1). Most of the correspondence covers the period, 1904 1910, although there are several items for 1912 and 1918. The correspondence contains information about the establishment of the ISS, activities of various ISS chapters, and routine organizational matters, such as sponsoring fund raising drives and scheduling speaking events and special conferences. Among the most prominent correspondents in this file are Harry W. Laidler, Upton Sinclair, William English Walling, James Graham Phelps Stokes, M. R. Holbrook, William Feigenbaum, Thomas Wentworth Higginson, W. J. Ghent, and John Spargo.
Two important, though not sizable, files in this collection are the Executive Committee minutes and the organizing Secretary reports. The Executive Committee minutes (XII:7) contain informative reports on ISS activities and proposed policy resolutions. This is undoubtedly the most complete set of Executive Committee minutes in existence, although some minutes are missing. The organizing Secretary reports (XII:8) document many of the activities which occurred in the ISS chapters throughout the country. These reports, which were written by Harry W. Laidler, also contain information about membership, new chapters, special events relating to the ISS, and financial matters. It should be emphasized that these reports are incomplete for the period covered in this file.
The printed, mimeographed, and office material (XII:9 XII:27) constitute the largest group of records in this collection. These papers are actually the contents of several ISS scrapbooks, which were compiled by Harry W. Laidler. The materials consist of memoranda, pamphlets, form letters, annual convention reports, lecture announcements, press releases, statements, and miscellaneous printed matter. These items have been arranged chronologically by year, month, and day, with undated items placed at the end of each year. The pamphlets and leaflets in these files have been bibliographically cited in the complete reel list under the particular file in which they are located.
This collection also contains most issues of the Bulletin of the Intercollegiate Socialist Society, 1908-1912, and a large number of newspaper clippings pertaining to the ISS. Serving as the major serial publication of the ISS during its formative period, the Bulletin of the Intercollegiate Socialist Society(XII:28) offers information about major policy developments and activities of the organization. The newspaper clippings (XII:29) were taken from a variety of socialist and non-socialist newspapers during the period, 1906 1918. These clippings contain information about the ISS's response to World War I, the ISS's idealistic visions of a socialist millennium, Rose Pastor Stokes and the controversy over distributing birth control information, the ISS's position regarding the 1912 and 1916 Presidential campaigns, and the important developments occurring at ISS meetings and quest lectures.
Arrangement
Folders are generally arranged chronologically with the exception of Series II which is arranged topically.
Arranged into six series:
Series I. Correspondence
Series II. Executive Committee & Administrative Materials
Series III. Printed, Mimeographed, and Office Materials
Series IV. Bulletin of the Intercollegiate Socialist Society
Series V. Newspaper Clippings
Series VI. Photographs
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Harry Laidler Papers (TAM 047)
Harry Laidler Photographs (PHOTOS 009)
Film R-7124, in the Tamiment Library, 1872-1956 (Film R-7124)
Film R-7124, in the Tamiment Library, 1872-1956: a Guide to the Microfilm Edition.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Due to the fragile nature of the original materials, researchers must use the microfilmed version; microfilm call number is Film R-7124, Reels 27-28. Series VI: Photographs is not available on microfilm.
Socialism -- United States.; Student movements.; Minutes (administrative records); Press releases.; Periodicals.; Clippings (information artifacts); Intercollegiate Socialist Society (U.S.); Laidler, Harry W. (Harry Wellington), 1884-1970; League for Industrial Democracy; Ghent, William J. (William James), 1866-1942; Holbrook, M. R.; Feigenbaum, William M., 1886-1949; Higginson, Thomas Wentworth, 1823-1911; Sinclair, Upton, 1878-1968; Walling, William English, 1877-1936; Stokes, James Graham Phelps, 1872-1960; Spargo, John, 1876-1966
- Series I. Correspondence, 71387
  - Correspondence, 1904; 71398 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Film R-7124, Reel 27, Frame XII:1
  - Correspondence, Jan 1905-Jun 1905; 71397 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, Jul 1905-Aug 1905; 71396; 3 folders 3, 3a, 3b (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, Sep 1905-Nov 1905; 71395 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, Dec 1905; 71394 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, Jan 1906-Jun 1906; 71393 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, Jul 1906-Dec 1906; 71392 (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
  - Correspondence, 1907; 71391 (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
  - Correspondence, 1908; 71390 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1909; 71389 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1910; 71388 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1918 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Series II. Executive Committee & Administrative Materials, 71374
  - Financial Papers, 1905-1917; 71386 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Film R-7124, Reel 27, Frame XII:2
  - Account Books, 1910-1912; 71385 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Film R-7124, Reel 27, Frame XII:3
  - Membership, Members of the Executive Committee, 1905-1921; 71384 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Film R-7124, Reel 27, Frame XII:4
  - Membership, Number of Chapters and Members, 1910-1917; 71383 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Film R-7124, Reel 27, Frame XII:5
  - Membership, Socialists on University Faculties, 1900-1920; 71382 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Film R-7124, Reel 27, Frame XII:6
  - Executive Committee Minutes, Sep 12, 1905-Dec 1906; 71381 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Film R-7124, Reel 27, Frame XII:7
  - Executive Committee Minutes, Apr 23, 1907-May 27, 1910; 71380 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Executive Committee Minutes, Sep 23, 1910-Nov 21, 1910; 71379 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Executive Committee Minutes, Jan 6, 1911-Apr 29, 1912; 71378 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Executive Committee Minutes, May 6, 1912-Dec 23, 1912; 71377 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Executive Committee Minutes, Jan 6, 1912-Apr 20, 1914; 71376 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Reports of Organizing Secretary (Incomplete), 1906-1921, undated; 71375 (Box 4, Folder 4-5)
    Film R-7124, Reel 27, Frame XII:8
- Series III. Printed, Mimeographed, and Office Materials, 71352
  - Contains: - Books on Socialism. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, 4pp.: 1905. - Intercollegiate Socialist Society. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, 4pp.: [1905]. - Weeks, Rufus. The Most Interesting Phenomenon of the Twentieth Century. Danville, Illinois: Christian Socialist Printing Company, 8pp. Reprint from Newark Evening News.: 1905. - Ford, E. B. You Must Do It. [Faribault, Minnesota]. 1p.: 1905 - Ford, Professor C. What Is Socialism? Who is a Socialist? np, 1p: [1905]., 71373 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    Film R-7124, Reel 27, Frame XII:9
  - Contains: - Patterson, Joseph Medill. Confessions of a Drone. Girard, Kansas: Appeal to Reason, [1906]. 14pp., 71372 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    Film R-7124, Reel 27, Frame XII:10
  - Contains: - Ross, E. A. Political Decay. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, [1907]. 4pp. - Sinclair, Upton. What Life Means To Me. Girard, Kansas: Appeal to Reason, (1907]. l2pp. - Intercollegiate Socialist Society. General Outline for a Course in the Study of Socialism, Suggested for Study Chapters of the Intercollegiate Socialist Society. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, 1907. 4pp. (2 copies), 71371 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    Film R-7124, Reel 27, Frame XII:11
  - Contains: - [Constitution of the Intercollegiate Socialist Society]. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, September 1908. 8pp. - A Few Socialists. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, [1908]. 4pp. - [Leaflet on the New York chapter of the Intercollegiate Socialist Society]. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, New York Chapter, [1908]. 7pp. - Spargo, John. Socialism and the Student. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, [1908]. 6pp. - Studies in Socialism. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, New York Chapter, [1908]. 3pp., 71370 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    Film R-7124, Reel 27, Frame XII:12
  - Contains: - Kirkpatrick, George R. For the Educated Proletariat. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, (1909). 20pp. - [Report by W. J. Ghent on the Intercollegiate Socialist Society]. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, October 1909. 8pp. - Lee, Algernon. What Socialists Stand For. New York: - Intercollegiate Socialist Society, (1909). 1pp., 71369 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Film R-7124, Reel 28, Frame XII:13
  - Contains: - [Report by Algernon Lee on the Intercollegiate Socialist Society]. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, September 1910. 8pp. - [Report on the New York chapter of the Intercollegiate Socialist Society]. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, September 1910. 7pp. - Socialism and the Student. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, 1910. 7pp., 71368 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    Film R-7124, Reel 28, Frame XII:14
  - Contains: - Books on Socialism and Allied Subjects. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, May 1911. 11pp. - Annual Statement of the Intercollegiate Socialist Society. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, September 1911. 16pp. - Socialism and the Student. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, December 1911. 11pp. - Study Chapters. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, December 1911. 8pp. - Socialism and the Student. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, [1911]. 7pp. - Ghent, W. J. To Skeptics and Doubters. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, 1911. 32pp., 71367 (Box 5, Folder 3-4)
    Film R-7124, Reel 28, Frame XII:15
  - Contains: - Members of the Intercollegiate Socialist Society. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, January 1912. 24pp. - Courses in Socialism. General outline for Courses in the Study of Socialism Suggested for Study Chapters of the Intercollegiate Socialist Society. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, September 1912. 15pp. - Annual Statement of the Intercollegiate Socialist Society. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, September 1912. 19pp. - Books on Socialism and Allied Subjects. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, December 1912. 11pp. - Study Chapters. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, March 1912. 8pp. - Socialism and Present Day Politics. Cambridge: Harvard Socialist Club, October 1912. Harvard Socialist Tracts No. 2. 8pp., 71366 (Box 5, Folder 5-6, Folder 1-2)
    Film R-7124, Reel 28, Frame XII:16
  - Scrapbooks, Jan 1913-May 1919; 71365 (Box 6, Folder 3-4)
    Film R-7124, Reel 28, Frame XII:17
  - Scrapbooks: - Annual Statement of the Intercollegiate Socialist Society. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, September 1913. 19pp. - [Leaflet of worker songs]. np, (1913). 5pp., Jun 1913-Dec 1919; 71364 (Box 6, Folder 5-6)
  - Contains: Study Chapters. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, February 1914. 8pp., Jan 1914-Oct 1914; 71363 (Box 6, Folder 7-8)
    Film R-7124, Reel 28, Frame XII:18
  - Contains: - Books on Socialism and Allied Subjects. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, September 1914. 12pp. - Socialism and Social Reform. Study Course. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, New York Chapter, [1914]. 4pp. - Laidler, Harry W. The European War and Socialism. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, New York Chapter, November 1914. 12pp., Nov 1914-Dec 1914; 71362 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Contains: Books on Socialism and Allied Subjects. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, December 1915. 4pp., 71361 (Box 7, Folder 2-3)
    Film R-7124, Reel 28, Frame XII:19
  - Contains: - Schoonmaker, Edwin Davies. The Greatest Lesson of War. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, 20pp. July 1916. - Why Study Socialism? New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, 20 pp., 1916. - Study Course on Socialism. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, 16 pp., 1916. - Perky, Cheves West. Cooperation in the United States. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, 31pp. [1916]. - Clark, Evans. Municipal Ownership in the United States. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, 30pp. [1916]., 71360 (Box 7, Folder 4-5)
    Film R-7124, Reel 28, Frame XII:20
  - Contains: - How to Organize. Suggestions to Members of the Intercollegiate Socialist Society. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, 4 pp., September 1917. - Membership List 1917 1918. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, 20 pp., [1917]., 71359 (Box 8, Folder 1-3)
    Film R-7124, Reel 28, Frame XII:21
  - Printed, Mimeographed, and Office Materials., 1918; 71358 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    Film R-7124, Reel 28, Frame XII:22
  - Contains: - Books on Socialism and Allied Subjects. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, 16 pp., February 1919 - Laidler, Harry W. Study Courses in Socialism. New York: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, 32 pp., February 1919, 71357 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    Film R-7124, Reel 28, Frame XII:23
  - Printed, Mimeographed, and Office Materials, 1920; 71356 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    Film R-7124, Reel 28, Frame XII:24
  - Printed, Mimeographed, and Office Materials, 1921; 71355 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    Film R-7124, Reel 28, Frame XII:25
  - Contains: London, Jack. What Life Means To Me. Princeton: Intercollegiate Socialist Society, 15 pp., undated; 71354 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    Film R-7124, Reel 28, Frame XII:26
  - Anti-Socialist Literature, contains: - Clum, Woodworth. Making Socialists Out of College Students. A Story of Professors and other Collegians Who Hobnob With Radicals. Los Angeles: Better American Federation of California, 23 pp., 1920; 71353 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    Film R-7124, Reel 28, Frame XII:27
  - Intercollegiate Socialist Society Event Poster, undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
- Series IV: Bulletin of the Intercollegiate Socialist Society, 71350
  - Bulletin of the Intercollegiate Socialist Society, contains: Dec 1, 1908; Mar-May, Oct-Nov 1909; Jan-Apr, Oct-Nov 1910; Dec 1910, Jan-May, Oct-Nov 1911; Dec 1911-Dec 1912, 1908-1912; 71351 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    Film R-7124, Reel 28, Frame XII:28
- Series V. Newspaper Clippings, 71346
  - Newspaper Clippings, Sep 1906-Dec 1910; 71349 (Box 9, Folder 2)
    Film R-7124, Reel 28, Frame XII:29
  - Newspaper Clippings, Jan 1911-Dec 1912; 71348 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Jan 1911-Dec 1916; 71347 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Sep 1913-Dec 1916; 553027 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Dec 1916-Sep 1918, undated; 553028 (Box 9, Folder 6)
- Series VI. Photographs, Sep 1916; 478844
  - Oversize, Sep 1916; 478846 (Flat-file-folder 2, Tray 2)
    Scope and Content Note
    Not microfilmed.